We have been looking at the dynamic programming
based methods for solving problems so far
and solving empty piece right so why do we
call them dynamic programming method so what
is the problem are we solving here what is
this a problem I actually give you the intuition
in assuming that you have a like remember
I talked about one step problems right as
I said that they can assume that the value
is one step problem.
Where for the first step you get the reward
and then you have a cost for termination or
a value for termination and I said you can
think of it as R plus ? times V so the ? V
is the value for termination right so if you
think about what we did for value iteration.
.
In order to use it so was it find it I introduced
the DARSI notation or there any resist explicitly
right so we did this similar mother so suppose
I am in a specific state right in which as
soon as I take a step the problem is right
the episode ends as soon as I take a step
the episode ends really it means I am not
asking you to hypothesis really the episode
names okay if I do this once on that if I
say let it start I start off with a zero value
function right so this part will be 0 in fact
this really does not play a role but anyway
this part will be 0 and then I will just get
the expected reward right so I take as I start
from the state okay.
Let us call with some S1 I take one step and
I end okay, some time will say I reach and
then you get a reward will say plus 1 or something
so the VN plus 1 I compute will be the value
function for s1 right just one time I do this
I will get the right value do you see what
I am saying so there is an end point right
if I look at the state just before the end
point that is the very first iteration I will
compute the right value for the state correct.
Let us say I have another state which is one
step before the s-1 right that is all that
is only transition available from S2 okay
so I take there is an action I take as to
and from which to I take the rational go test
one okay so how many iterations should I run
before I get the value for is 2 so one way
of thinking about what this is doing is to
say that this computes a solution for n step
problem it computes the solution for an N
step problem.
And assuming that I start from s prime I will
end in n steps this gives me the value right
and this concludes the value for n + 1 right
so that is essentially where thee the dynamic
programming aspect comes in so the smaller
problem the sub problem is solved is the one
for the end step prediction right and then
the larger problem I solve is using this repeat
the substructure so the value of n + one prediction
will be R plus the value of n prediction so
this using this sub problems and making it
I am trying to solve the larger problem makes
it a dynamic programming.
I is stochastic dynamic programming is typically
called stochastic dynamic programming because
you mean all this to cast city is there right
and it is really this works are in respective
of whether it is a finite horizon problem
or not right so assuming you stop in one step
what is the solution right here I am saying
you actually get to the terminal state but
you can just think about forget about terminal
state any state can be terminal straight but.
I allow you to act for only one time step
I will elevate act for two time steps three
times for time steps and I keep going to allow
you to act for an infinite number of time
steps right so that is essentially what value
iteration this so it is like a dynamic programming
approach right that is why we see you solve
for n and then you use that sub problem solution
to solve for n plus 1 okay, so that is why
it is called dynamic program.
I said clear right so these classes of methods
both value iteration and policy iteration
So policy situation also has dynamic programming
method which is a little tricky to see what
the dynamic programming dynamic program there
is but still it is also a dynamic programming
approach and so I am going to talk about a
general class of dynamic programming solution
here but before that I want to introduce one
other distinction actually a couple more distinction.
So there is something called a synchronous
dynamic programming so if you think about
this is one step in the value iteration that
means I am assuming most people who in here
have that in your notebook so I am not going
to write out the entire value iteration procedure
right so that is one step right that is one
iteration in think that is the main iteration
in the value iteration algorithm right.
So what is the crucial thing to note here
is that for all the VN + 1 computation right
I use VN on the right hand side right so one
way of thinking about it is okay I have this
array right now I have this data structure
some array that represents the value function
at time n so I use the array and compute the
value function at time n plus 1 so it is a
different array right so I make it says I
have n and then I make another array which
is n + 1 and they compute it and then I copy
that n plus 1 over 2n and then keep doing
this right.
Instead of that you could think of a way of
doing it where I do this in place I do not
use to erase I do not use one array for n1
a referendum I can do it with a single array
so what that would mean is when I suppose
I have some ordering on the state still have
to go through some loop on the state's say
for s equal one to n or something like that
say so when I do a s = 1 right I will be using
the old values of V n so I will be using VN
right.
So when I use s =2 here I will be using VN
for 2 3 4 5 2 n but I will use VN plus 1 for
1 likewise when I use VN + 1 of 3 when I am
computing it I will be computing VN + 1 of
2 and 1 and VN of all the other states okay.
Now this is a little tricky if you think about
it because it is not clear what I am doing
right there it is VN + 1 or VN + 2 suppose
I come to state 5 okay and all the transition
from five is going to state 1 & 2 so when
I am actually computing me n plus 1 of 5 I
will be using VN + 1 of 1 and V n + 1 of 2
so is it I am a competing GN +1of five.
Or I am computing VN + 2 of everything the
second iterate off I am using one further
literate of one and two right. So in fact
it is not even clear whether if you do it
this way it will converge or not right turns
out it will converge right and it turns out
that I do not even have to do it in this kind
of a you know sequential order and I can do
it I can pick any state right and then update
its value and then pick some other state right
now then update its value I can keep randomly
picking states and keep updating their value
using whatever is the current stored value
of its neighbors right.
So instead of using that right so I can do
this I mean from an array point of view right
so whenever I update some value this is all
the Eigen side also will change I guess keep
picking states and I can do this right so
this is called as synchronous mode for running
dynamic programming so the only condition
I need now to make sure this dynamic programming
converges is
I have to say I love our from the other things
in it an additional condition I have to assume
I have to ensure is that I sample all the
states at least
infinite number of times so that I can ensure
convergence okay. I am just waiting I give
you a rock Q as I think it is equally guys
will do, but I have to apply the update in
every state infinite number of times for it
to converge right.
So that is the convergence criterion we saw
earlier and only as this the iterates tend
to infinity we have looked at all the the
fixed point theorems only as a traits tend
to infinity do we converge right. So in that
case so we have to make sure that all the
states are sampled infinitely often right
so then it will converge. So it turns out
it does not matter in what order example may
say actually very powerful reason.
And it allows us to do a whole bunch of interesting
stuff right in fact it allows us to do something
called real-time dynamic programming which
is a very interesting algorithm which is almost
like reinforcement learning but not quite
there okay. So one of the main problems in
doing value iteration and policy creation
and things like that is when you are working
with really large state spaces right when
you are working with really large state spaces
you will be every time you do this iteration
right.
Whether do it in the synchronous on a thickness
fashion so every time you do this iteration
right you basically run through all the states.
So in fact if you think about the amount of
effort you spend in computing the solution
you spend the same effort in computing the
value function for every state right, but
that is not often needed if you think about
any practical problem there are many, many
states which are very seldom visited right.
So you want to spend more effort in trying
to discover the true value function for states
that you visit often right, and states that
you very rarely visit you do not mind right.
So if people remember the the expected error
formulation that we used in machine learning
right so we always try to vary the error by
the probability of actually seeing the data
point. So like that here I would like to if
I want to try to do an optimization I would
like to weigh the error with the probability
of me actually visiting that state.
So now I have some estimate some BBB hat of
S right so when I am evaluating my performance
I look at the true V*-V hat right times the
probability of going to yes right, this is
a, so why do I want to do that why do not
you, common sense things yeah, you do not
have infinite computational power I mean,
we just say nicely run none thing still infinity
you really do not have infinite computational
power.
So that is why we gave you some epsilon criterion
so you can sadly satisfy the epsilon optimal
policies and so on so forth it so you do not
have to run till infinity but if I give you
a mdp which has say 100 million states
so I do not even want to run into finite number
of times on all the states right that is a
still a significant amount of computation
usually a limited amount of computation.
So now we have to figure out how am I going
to assign this limited amount of computation
and how am I going to spend this limited amount
of computation. So what you would really like
to do is spend a lot of time on those states
which you are likely to visit under an optimal
policy. So you do not want to miss out on
states which are good with which you need
to execute an optimal policy right.
So one way that people do it is the following
right, they start from some state, they execute
some trajectory right then they look at states
that occur along those trajectory right and
do the dynamic programming updates only on
those states. Then what you do is now you
have a value function right you have made
some changes to the value function and this
implicitly gives you a policy, so we all know
that right.
So you know how to recover the policy given
a value function, so I looked at it we looked
at it from V look at it from Q given a V function
you know how to recover their policy, given
a Q function you know how to recover a policy.
So now recover the policy from this value
function okay. Now run another trajectory
just by running this policy so it is like
a sample you are taking from the world.
So it starts from the starting state execute
this policy see which are the states that
you visit right and then run your updates
on those states, but the crucial thing to
remember here is that every state you are
running your dynamic programming update like
this we are assuming that you know their expected
value of the reward you are assuming you know
your transition probabilities and then with
these you are changing the value right.
So I am not worried about what was the sample
I am getting here if you think of the Bandit
case whenever I draw a sample I get just one
reward right. So in this case what we are
using the sampling for just to determine which
are the states that which we have to do the
update right. So not in the reward and all
that we assume that the reward distribution
everything is given to us we are only doing
the sampling to figure out which are the states
we have to do the updates.
So it is called real-time dynamic programming
I mean the real time is within coats here
that is because you are generating these trajectories
using the current policy. So the idea is that
as your policy as your value function gets
closer and closer to the optimal value function
the policies become closer and closer to the
optimal policies and therefore the set of
states that you sample will be those that
are highly likely to appear under those trajectories
right.
For example, if I have to start here and go
here right states at all to the corners might
not get some sample that often you know I
will probably start trying to go in a straight
line from here to here so we will start going
like this after sometime. So you can see that
there will be some kind of like an envelope
of states that will get sampled a lot right
and I will be applying the the the DP updates
on those states more than DP updates on the
side other things.
Yeah sure, so I did not talk about exploitation
here so, you never behave getting you with
respect to the value function we always have
some kind of exploration you could ? greedy.
So you know about ? greedy right. So at every
point so I look at the values of the actions
or values of the next state and be greedy
only with the probability 1 - ? and then the
probability of ? I do something right yeah
you should do something ? right yeah.
So this is called real-time dynamic program
it is actually a pretty powerful method provided
you have a model available to you this allows
you to focus your computation only on a small
number of states okay. But if you want to
ensure convergence in real time dynamic programming
right what is the condition you need, you
have to visit every state infinitely often
I mean, so does not matter that you are focusing
your computation.
So what essentially dynamic programming allows
you to do is that given a finite number of
updates that you can do okay it allows you
to focus those finite number of updates in
things are in states which are more likely
to be useful to you right. But given an infinite
amount of computation it will eventually converge
assuming that you have an ? said never going
to zero okay.
So crucial thing that you should note here
is we will have the DP we use the sampling
only to figure out which states to update
okay nothing more than that. If you move on
when we actually look at true reinforcement
learning algorithms you will be using the
sampling to determine not only the states
to update right but also what is the reward
that you have to update it with because I
do not have this reward right.
And also what is the the terminal cost you
will use here what is the VS’ you will use
here because this also I do not have this
is why I said, this takes you some ways towards
a full reinforcement learning algorithm but
it is still a dynamic programming solution
because it uses all the expectations okay
good any questions on this.
So how many of you have been reading ahead
on this is what chapter is am I on in the
book okay good how many of you have read chapter
four you are my only hope man come on disappointed
only gate has been reading so far yeah anyway
yeah so I do not think our TDP is that in
Chapter four so whatever I told you is the
thing if you want to read more and probably
have to pick up the rtd be paper it actually
is very well written the version lottery if
you captain of course I am a big fan of Andy's
writing.
So I always say that but so the next thing
I want to talk about this very very powerful
technique that we use called the generalized
policy iteration people remember policy iteration
right so they say essentially has two steps
right so you have policy evaluation and then
you have policy improvement
so what is the synchronous just checking if
people are listening you can look we are so
you do not have to do it in last step right.
All the states do not have to get updated
in one iteration right so there is no actual
definition iteration itself is gone here as
synchronous state, but anyway so people know
me that is policy iteration right. So I have
a policy evaluation step right and then have
a policy improvement step the PI stands for
policy improvement not policy iteration right.
Policy evaluation policy improvement I keep
doing this until my policy does not change
anymore right and so we did do the convergence
of policy iteration then I can kind of convince
you that policy iteration would converge at
least on finite in degrees. So we have not
done the convergence on its infinite state
spaces I am not going to do that because most
of the results I will be showing you will
be only on finite state spaces.
Mainly because I need to develop a lot more
mechanism for showing you this on infinite
state paces and it really belongs to a course
on one mdp not on RL right. So it really belongs
to a course on mdp so if interest rate I do
not know Sir Rachal Murata used to teach a
course in dorms on MVPs I do not think he
does that anymore he actually used to teach
out of cysts.
So whatever book I have been using to get
all this material for you it's called Markov
decision processes by put in on so what do
we have a copies of the chapters from put
minus on this earth I do not tell me if there
is an online version of put man but maybe
you should tell them not me we do not have
a version of Phutra Marissa did they give
one last year I think you can pick it up from
the last years material or something whatever
yeah do not try to read it right.
So what is essentially did was took three
different chapters from the book and cherry
picked results that I wanted to present here
and then kind of you know simplified the theorems
and other proofs and so on so forth and presented
it to you so if you actually read put Herman
directly it in fact some of you might being
confused as to where the heck of those theorems
he did in class in the book right but I assure
you that the place to go if you want to understand
this better.
And that is where I took this material from
anyway so going back to policy iteration right
so there is this technique called generalized
policy iteration somewhat like a synchronous
DP right in the sense that it does the following
so I have a policy I have evaluated the policy
right I do not try to be greedy on all the
states in the value function I just pick some
states right.
And then I say okay I am going to change my
policy by being greedy only here
right then I go back and do the evaluation
of this new policy
but then we have to evaluate this new policy
in every state only which are updated not
really I have to I learned it a little bit
more because states that are close by which
moving here their values will also change
because this values change.
So I have to do some amount of evaluation
around the states where I change it right
in fact it turns out that this works both
ways so I start off with a policy I do not
evaluate it on every state okay evaluated
only on some states just like we did in our
theory p it actually DPI did value iteration
right guidance of doing value iteration right
I would have taken off this max here right
I could have put a summation over p SI, so
I start off with some arbitrary p it run this
update only on trajectories right.
Now I will sample some states I will update
the value function therefore the current p
that I am following right and then what I
do now I go try to be greedy with respect
to this value function now here it makes sense
only to be greedy with respect to those states
in which no need to be greedy in those states
in which you change the value function because
other states it would not change okay.
I am only looking at the value function and
I try to be greedy right so it will not change
but in those states where I change the value
function I have gone do the clarification
I'll change the policy now now what I do have
a new policy I can go back and sample some
more states according to this new policy and
into the policy evaluation only on those states
at a sample so I am doing both a partial policy
evaluation and a partial policy improvement
this is called generalized policy improvement
right.
So one way of thinking about it is that instead
of that's a picture in the book if you do
not like so instead of doing a complete evaluation
or a complete improvement you are doing this
partially bit bits and pieces right so why
do you want to do this again you can save
computation yeah you have to remember thee
in which you did the policy evaluation in
policy or even you do not really have to the
most effect you will get is if you do the
policy improvement only on the states where
we evaluated the policy right.
But you don't have to so I can always say
that I will pick some random number of states
and then I will go I will pick some random
set of states I will do my policy evaluation
there I will go pick another random set of
states and term a policy improvement that
if the intersection is empty then you are
probably not change my policy at all but that
should not be your shopping criterion so you
should have a different stopping criterion
we are doing generalized Paula situation right.
But the feed intersection is empty you wouldn't
stop and then when you would not change the
policy go back and sample some more states
so that way if you do you will be doing a
lot of wasteful computation when the ball
the policy improvement it it'd be wasted but
you do not need to remember it is more useful
if you do it on trajectories so why is that
I mean technically I mean the rtdp style of
convergence rate I mean if I do not do it
on trajectories it becomes more or less like
a synchronous DP right but I am claiming that
are TDP will have a greater effect than a
synchronous tpy I am sorry.
Not just happen more often there is a slightly
subtle point here but I am looking along the
trajectory so I am actually not only sampling
a state I am also sampling a successor I am
sampling a successor and sampling a successor
so that will be changes you know when I am
going to update VN + 1 off remember I put
in some space like so other day of sample
guess three right I will re compute the value
of S3 ?? that also affect the value of s 2
right so now because I'm sampling along the
trajectory I will actually get this sequence
here.
So when it when it update is three my stool
also get updated my phone will also get updated
so because of this connectedness right so
I actually have a greater effect for that
sample I drew that if had sample some S1 somewhere
and this to somewhere else and they are not
connected there is no way they are going to
win appear in each other's update equations
right then I will be using the same world
values that I had and I will be trying to
update this so that is why so sampling along
a trajectory can be more effective.
So you want to sample opposite race again
you do not have to right so what we are trying
to do is so even how to in the in the sense
of time to show convergence right all you
need to do to show convergence is you sample
it infinitely enough right so you don't have
to show that the samples are long trajectories
right it is possible that the few wits a little
know with a lot of work you can show that
by your rate of convergence improves if you
are sampling along trajectories.
But I am not aware of any search results that
people have actually worked out there maybe
just because it is too hard to show and it's
not that much of an interesting result anyway
but the people get the idea began generalized
policy iteration right. In fact you can take
generalized policy iteration to an extreme
how, I can sample a state okay, taken one
action according to the policy we have right
and then be greedy with respect to the updated
value function.
So sample state take one action right, update
the value of the state now be greedy disrespect
to that and produce a new policy only for
that state I will change the action right,
sounds too extreme, right so this is policy
evaluation policy improvement we talked about
it I just take some trajectories I do the
policy evaluation on that and then I do policy
improvement and I keep iterating this and
I am claiming it will converge, okay so I
am not going to show you proofs of generalized
policy iteration converging.
But I am claiming that will converge and trust
me right, now the question I am asking you
is I am doing this one day on one state at
a time pick a state, I pick an action according
to the policy right and then I update the
value function and then I change the policy
for the state to be greedy with respect to
that value function. I can do this by randomly
sampling states over the thing or I can do
this way sweeping through states I start with
this s1 I will do this and change the policy
they I will start with S2 is change the policy
there and keep doing this, as it sound like
a reasonable thing to do.
Why I just look at the value function and
then pick that one action it gives me the
maximum value right, so that is what I mean
by greedy is that I am not saying that I have
only one choice to make choose from I am saying
I have to take only one action I have multiple
choices among those i picked the one that
is greedy with respect to the very function.
No we have already looked at an algorithm
that does that that is exactly what value
iteration does if you think about it, right.
So I pick the best action right so being greedy
I pick one step and then I find out what the
next thing is and use that I update the value
function, so the next time I come to the state
I will pick the best action according to the
new iterate of the value function, right so
this is essentially what value iteration does
is one way of thinking about value iteration
is an extreme form of generalized policy iteration
and you pick a state right, pick a greedy
action, right evaluate the policy then change
the policy right.
So in fact we are learning the policy evaluation
in the policy improvement step has been rolled
into one equation there can a crazy right,
so that is what value iteration is in think
of it as generalized extreme power of 10 based
policy inflation so that does not appeal to
you do not worry about it right but what we
will do later is that many of the reinforcement
learning algorithms that we will look at or
some form or the other of generalized policy
iteration.
So many, many, many cases that we look at
is some form or the other of generalized policy
iteration and so one of the powers of power
of generalized policy iteration is the following
so as soon as I come up with a mechanism by
which I can evaluate a policy, if I give you
some policy I can evaluate the policy hey,
that is all you know right I can use that
and to enter it into mechanism for learning
to solve the MDP right.
If I give a mechanism for evaluating a policy
I can turn that into mechanism for solving
the MDP just saying that I am going to repeatedly
evaluate policies and then improve between
the evaluations, let us as soon as I define
that policy evaluation scheme I can convert
that into a solution for the MDP itself, so
this is essentially the framework that we
will see in many of the reinforcement learning
algorithms we look at, so we will first look
at the evaluation set up and then we look
at the optimal solution setup, okay.